<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std"
     docName="draft-kaliraj-idr-bgp-classful-transport-planes-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BGP Classful Transport Planes">BGP Classful Transport
    Planes</title>

    <author fullname="Kaliraj Vairavakkalai" initials="K."
            surname="Vairavakkalai">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1133 Innovation Way,</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94089</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>kaliraj@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Natrajan Venkataraman" initials="N."
            surname="Venkataraman">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1133 Innovation Way,</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94089</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>natv@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Balaji Rajagopalan" initials="B." surname="Rajagopalan">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Electra, Exora Business Park~Marathahalli - Sarjapur Outer
          Ring Road,</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>KA</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>balajir@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="13" month="July" year="2020"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies a mechanism, referred to as "service
      mapping", to express association of overlay routes with underlay routes
      using BGP. The document describes a framework for classifying underlay
      routes into transport planes, and mapping service routes to specific
      transport plane. It specifies BGP protocol procedures that enable
      dissimination of such service mapping information that may span across
      administrative domains. It makes it possible to advertise multiple
      tunnels to the same destination.</t>

      <t>A new BGP transport address family is defined for this purpose that
      uses RFC-4364 technology and follows RFC-8277 NLRI encoding. This new
      address family is called "Classful Transport".</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>To facilitate service mapping, the tunnels in a network can be
      grouped by the purpose they serve into a "Transport Class". The tunnels
      could be created using any signaling protocol, such as LDP, RSVP, BGP-LU
      or SPRING. The tunnels could also use native IP or IPv6, as long as they
      can carry MPLS payload. Tunnels may exist between different pair of end
      points. Multiple tunnels may exist between the same pair of end
      points.</t>

      <t>Thus, a Transport Class consists of tunnels created by various
      protocols, and satisfy the properties of the class. For example, a
      "Gold" transport class may consist of tunnels that traverse the shortest
      path with fast re-route protection, a "Silver" transport class may hold
      tunnels that traverse shortest paths without protection, a "To NbrAS
      Foo" transport class may hold tunnels that exit to neighboring AS Foo,
      and so on.</t>

      <t>The extensions specified in this document can be used to create a BGP
      transport tunnel that potentially spans domains, while preserving its
      Transport Class. Examples of domain are Autonomous System (AS), or IGP
      area. Within each domain, there is a second level underlay tunnel used
      by BGP to cross the domain. The second level underlay tunnels could be
      hetrogeneous: Each domain may use a different type of tunnel, or use a
      differnet signaling protocol. A domain boundary is demarcated by a
      rewrite of BGP nexthop to 'self' while re-advertising tunnel routes in
      BGP. Examples of domain boundary are inter-AS links and inter-region
      ABRs. The path uses MPLS label-switching when crossing domain boundary
      and uses the native intra-AS tunnel of the desired transport class when
      traversing within a domain.</t>

      <t>Overlay routes carry sufficient indication of the Transport Classes
      they should be encapsulated over, in form of BGP community called the
      "mapping community". Based on the mapping community, "route resolution"
      procedure on the ingress node selects from the corresponding Transport
      Class an appropriate tunnel whose destination matches (LPM) the nexthop
      of the overlay route. If the overlay route is carried in BGP, the
      protocol nexthop (or, PNH) is generally carried as an attribute of the
      route. The PNH of the overlay route is also referred to as "service
      endpoint". The service endpoint may exist in the same domain as the
      service ingress node or lie in a different domain, adjacent or
      non-adjacent.</t>

      <t>This document describes mechanisms to: <list>
          <t>Model a "Transport Class" as "Transport RIB" on a router,
          consisting of tunnel ingress routes of a certain class.</t>

          <t>Enable service routes to resolve over an intended Transport Class
          by virtue of carrying the appropriate "Mapping community". Which
          results in using the corresponding Transport RIB for finding nexthop
          reachability.</t>

          <t>Advertise tunnel ingress routes in a Transport RIB via BGP
          without any path hiding, using BGP VPN technology and Add-path. Such
          that overlay routes in the receiving domains can also resolve over
          tunnels of associated Transport Class.</t>

          <t>Provide a way for co-operating domains to reconcile between
          independently administered extended community namespaces, and
          interoperate between different transport signaling protocols in each
          domain.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>In this document we focus mainly on MPLS LSPs as transport tunnels,
      but the mechanisms would work in similar manner for non-MPLS transport
      tunnels too, provided the tunnel can carry MPLS payload.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>LSP: Label Switched Path</t>

      <t>TE : Traffic Engineering</t>

      <t>SN : Service Node</t>

      <t>BN : Border Node</t>

      <t>TN : Transport Node, P-router</t>

      <t>BGP-VPN : VPNs built using RFC4364 mechanisms</t>

      <t>RT : Route-Target extended community</t>

      <t>RD : Route-Distinguisher</t>

      <t>PNH : Protocol-Nexthop address carried in a BGP Update message</t>

      <t>LPM : Longest Prefix Match</t>

      <t>Service Family : BGP address family used for advertising routes for
      "data traffic", as opposed to tunnels</t>

      <t>Transport Family : BGP address family used for advertising tunnels,
      which are in turn used by service routes for resolution</t>

      <t>Transport Tunnel : A tunnel over which a service may place traffic.
      These tunnels can be GRE, UDP, LDP, RSVP, or SR-TE</t>

      <t>Tunnel Domain : A domain of the network containing SN and BN, under a
      single administrative control that has a tunnel between SN and BN. An
      end-to-end tunnel spanning several adjacent tunnel domains can be
      created by "stitching" them together using labels.</t>

      <t>Transport Class : A group of transport tunnels offering the same type
      of service.</t>

      <t>Transport Class RT : A Route-Target extended community used to
      identify a specific Transport Class</t>

      <t>Transport RIB : At the SN and BN, a Transport Class has an associted
      Transport RIB that holds its tunnel routes.</t>

      <t>Transport Plane : An end to end plane comprising of transport tunnels
      belonging to same transport class. Tunnels of same transport class are
      stitched together by BGP route readvertisements with nexthop-self, to
      span across domain boundaries using Label-Swap forwarding mechanism
      similar to Inter-AS option-b.</t>

      <t>Mapping Community : BGP Community/Extended-community on a service
      route, that maps it to resolve over a Transport Class</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Transport Class">
      <t>A Transport Class is defined as a set of transport tunnels that share
      certain characteristics useful for underlay selection.</t>

      <t>On the wire, a transport class is represented as the Transport Class
      RT, which is a new Route-Target extended community.</t>

      <t>A Transport Class is configured at SN and BN, along with attributes
      like RD and Route-Target. Creation of a Transport Class instantiates the
      associated Transport RIB and a Transport routing instance to contain
      them all.</t>

      <t>The operator may configure a SN/BN to classify a tunnel into an
      appropriate Transport Class, which causes the tunnel's ingress routes to
      be installed in the corresponding Transport RIB. At a BN, these tunnel
      routes may then be advertised into BGP.</t>

      <t>Alternatively, a router receiving the transport routes in BGP with
      appropriate signaling information can associate those ingress routes to
      the appropriate Transport Class. E.g. for Classful Transport family
      (SAFI 76) routes, the Transport Class RT indicates the Transport Class.
      For BGP-LU family(SAFI 4) routes, import processing based on Communities
      or inter-AS source-peer may be used to place the route in the desired
      Transport Class.</t>

      <t>When the ingress route is received via <xref
      target="SRTE">SRTE</xref>, which encodes the Transport Class as an
      integer 'Color' in the NLRI as "Color:Endpoint", the 'Color' is mapped
      to a Transport Class during import processing. SRTE ingress route for
      'Endpoint' is installed in that transport-class. The SRTE route when
      advertised out to BGP speakers will then be advertised in Classful
      Transport family with Transport Class RT and a new label. The MPLS swap
      route thus installed for the new label will pop the label and deliver
      decapsulated-traffic into the path determined by SRTE route.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="&quot;Transport Class&quot; Route Target Extended Community">
      <t>This document defines a new type of Route Target, called "Transport
      Class" Route Target Extended Community.</t>

      <t>"Transport Class" Route Target extended community is a transitive
      extended community <xref target="RFC4360">EXT-COMM</xref> of
      extended-type, with a new Format (Type high = 0xa) and SubType as 0x2
      (Route Target).</t>

      <t>This new Route Target Format has the following encoding:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork> 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Type= 0xa   | SubType= 0x02 |            Reserved           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                     Transport Class                           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

         "Transport Class" Route Target Extended Community

 Type: Type field contains value 0xa.

 SubType: Subtype field contain 0x2. This indicates 'Route Target'.

 Transport Class: The least significant 32-bits of the value field
 contain the "Transport Class" value, which is a 32-bit integer. 

 The remaining 2 octets after SubType field are Reserved, they MUST 
 be ignored on reception, and set to zero on transmission.
</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The "Transport class" Route Target Extended community follows the
      mechanisms for VPN route leaking and RTC as sspecified in <xref
      target="RFC4364">BGP-VPN</xref> and <xref
      target="RFC4684">VPN-RTC</xref></t>

      <t>The Transport Class Route Target Extended community is carried on
      Classful Transport family routes, and allows associating them with
      appropriate Transport RIBs at receiving BGP speakers.</t>

      <t>Use of the Transport Class Route Target Extended community with a new
      Type code avoids conflicts with any VPN Route Target assignments already
      in use for service families.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Transport RIB">
      <t>A Transport RIB is a routing-only RIB that is not installed in
      forwarding path. However, the routes in this RIB are used to resolve
      reachability of overlay routes' PNH. Transport RIB is created when the
      Transport Class it represents is configured.</t>

      <t>Overlay routes that want to use a specific Transport Class confine
      the scope of nexthop resolution to the set of routes contained in the
      corresponding Transport RIB. This Transport RIB is the "Routing Table"
      referred in <eref
      target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4271#section-9.1.2.1">Section
      9.1.2.1 RFC4271</eref></t>

      <t>Routes in a Transport RIB are exported out in 'Classful Transport'
      address family.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Transport Routing Instance">
      <t>A BGP VPN routing instance that is a container for the Transport RIB.
      It imports, and exports routes in this RIB with Transport Class RT.
      Tunnel destination addresses in this routing instance's context come
      from the "provider namespace". This is different from user VRFs for
      e.g., which contain prefixes in "customer namespace"</t>

      <t>The Transport Routing instance uses the RD and RT configured for the
      Transport Class.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Nexthop Resolution Scheme">
      <t>An implementation may provide an option for the service route to
      resolve over less preferred Transport Classes, should the resolution
      over preferred, or "primary" Transport Class fail.</t>

      <t>To accomplish this, the set of service routes may be associated with
      a user-configured "resolution scheme", which consists of the primary
      Transport Class, and optionally, an ordered list of fallback Transport
      Classes.</t>

      <t>A community called as "Mapping Community" is configured for a
      "resolution scheme". A Mapping community maps to exactly one resolution
      scheme. A resolution scheme comprises of one primary transport class and
      optionally one or more fallback transport classes.</t>

      <t>When a resolution scheme comprises of a primary Transport Class
      without any fallback, the Transport Class RT associated with the primary
      Transport Class is used as the Mapping Community.</t>

      <t>A BGP route is associated with a resolution scheme during import
      processing. The first community on the route that matches a mapping
      community of a locally configured resolution scheme is considered the
      effective mapping community for the route. The resolution scheme thus
      found is used when resolving the route's PNH. If a route contains more
      than one mapping community, it indicates that the route considers these
      multiple mapping communities as equivalent. So the first community that
      maps to a resolution scheme is chosen.</t>

      <t>A transport route received in BGP Classful Transport family SHOULD
      use a resolution scheme that contains the primary Transport Class
      without any fallback to best effort tunnels. The primary Transport Class
      is identified by the Transport Class RT carried on the route. Thus
      Transport Class RT serves as the Mapping Community for Classful
      Transport routes.</t>

      <t>A service route received in a BGP service family MAY map to a
      resolution scheme that contains the primary Transport Class identified
      by the mapping community on the route, and a fallback to best effort
      tunnels transport class. The primary Transport Class is identified by
      the Mapping community carried on the route. For e.g. the Extended Color
      community may serve as the Mapping Community for service routes.
      Color:0:&lt;n&gt; MAY map to a resolution scheme that has primary
      transport class &lt;n&gt;, and a fallback to best-effort transport
      class.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="BGP Classful Transport Family NLRI">
      <t>The Classful Transport family will use the existing AFI of IPv4 or
      IPv6, and a new SAFI 76 "Classful Transport" that will apply to both
      IPv4 and IPv6 AFIs.</t>

      <t>The "Classful Transport" SAFI NLRI itself is encoded as specified in
      <xref
      target="RFC8277">https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8277#section-2</xref>.</t>

      <t>When AFI is IPv4 the "Prefix" portion of Classful Transport family
      NLRI consists of an 8-byte RD followed by an IPv4 prefix. When AFI is
      IPv6 the "Prefix" consists of an 8-byte RD followed by an IPv6
      prefix.</t>

      <t>Attributes on a Classful Transport route include the Transport Class
      Route-Target extended community, which is used to leak the route into
      the right Transport RIBs on SNs and BNs in the network.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Comparison with other families using RFC-8277 encoding">
      <t>SAFI 128 (Inet-VPN) is a RF8277 encoded family that carries service
      prefixes in the NLRI, where the prefixes come from the customer
      namespaces, and are contexualized into separate user virtual service
      RIBs called VRFs, using RFC4364 procedures.</t>

      <t>SAFI 4 (BGP-LU) is a RFC8277 encoded family that carries transport
      prefixes in the NLRI, where the prefixes come from the provider
      namespace.</t>

      <t>SAFI 76 (Classful Transport) is a RFC8277 encoded family that carries
      transport prefixes in the NLRI, where the prefixes come from the
      provider namespace, but are contexualized into separate Transport RIBs,
      using RFC4364 procedures.</t>

      <t>It is worth noting that SAFI 128 has been used to carry transport
      prefixes in "L3VPN Inter-AS Carrier's carrier" scenario, where
      BGP-LU/LDP prefixes in CsC VRF are advertised in SAFI 128 to the
      remote-end baby carrier.</t>

      <t>In this document a new AFI/SAFI is used instead of reusing SAFI 128
      to carry these transport routes, because it is operationally
      advantageous to segregate transport and service prefixes into separate
      address families, RIBs. E.g. It allows to safely enable "per-prefix"
      label allocation scheme for Classful Transport prefixes without
      affecting SAFI 128 service prefixes which may have huge scale. "per
      prefix" label allocation scheme keeps the routing churn local during
      topology changes. A new family also facilitates having a different
      readvertisement path of the transport family routes in a network than
      the service route readvertisement path. viz. Service routes (Inet-VPN)
      are exchanged over an EBGP multihop sessions between Autonomous systems
      with nexthop unchanged; whereas Classful Transport routes are
      readvertised over EBGP single hop sessions with "nexthop-self" rewrite
      over inter-AS links.</t>

      <t>The Classful Transport family is similar in vein to BGP-LU, in that
      it carries transport prefixes. The only difference is, it also carries
      in Route Target an indication of which Transport Class the transport
      prefix belongs to, and uses RD to disambiguate multiple instances of the
      same transport prefix in a BGP Update.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Protocol Procedures">
      <t>This section summarizes the procedures followed by various nodes
      speaking Classful Transport family</t>

      <t>Preparing the network for deploying Classful Transport planes</t>

      <t><list>
          <t>Operator decides on the Transport Classes that exist in the
          network, and allocates a Route-Target to identify each Transport
          Class.</t>

          <t>Operator configures Transport Classes on the SNs and BNs in the
          network with unique Route-Distinguishers and Route-Targets.</t>

          <t>Implementations may provide automatic generation and assignment
          of RD, RT values for a transport routing instance; they MAY also
          provide a way to manually override the automatic mechanism, in order
          to deal with any conflicts that may arise with existing RD, RT
          values in the different network domains participating in a
          deployment.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Origination of Classful Transport route:</t>

      <t><list>
          <t>At the ingress node of the tunnel's home domain, the tunneling
          protocols install routes in the Transport RIB associated with the
          Transport Class the tunnel belongs to. The ingress node then
          advertises this tunnel route into BGP as a Classful Transport route
          with NLRI RD:TunnelEndpoint, attaching a Route-Target that
          identifies the Transport Class.</t>

          <t>Alternatively, the egress node of the tunnel i.e. the tunnel
          endpoint can originate the BGP Classful Transport route, with NLRI
          RD:TunnelEndpoint and PNH TunnelEndpoint, which will resolve over
          the tunnel route at the ingress node. When the tunnel is up, the
          Classful Transport BGP route will become usable and get
          re-advertised.</t>

          <t>Unique RD is used by the originator of a Classful Transport route
          to disambiguate the multiple BGP advertisements for a transport end
          point.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Ingress node receiving Classful Transport route<list>
          <t>On receiving a BGP Classful Transport route with a PNH that is
          not directly connected, e.g. an IBGP-route, a mapping community on
          the route (the Transport Class RT) indicates which Transport Class
          this route maps to. The routes in the associated Transport RIB are
          used to resolve the received PNH. If there does not exist a route in
          the Transport RIB matching the PNH, the Classful Transport route is
          considered unusable, and MUST NOT be re-advertised further.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Border node readvertising Classful Transport route with nexthop
      self:<list>
          <t>The BN allocates an MPLS label to advertise upstream in Classful
          Transport NLRI. The BN also installs an MPLS swap-route for that
          label that swaps the incoming label with a label received from the
          downstream BGP speaker, or pops the incoming label. And then pushes
          received traffic to the transport tunnel or direct interface that
          the Classful Transport route's PNH resolved over.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Border node receiving Classful Transport route on EBGP :<list>
          <t>If the route is received with PNH that is known to be directly
          connected, e.g. EBGP single-hop peering address, the directly
          connected interface is checked for MPLS forwarding capability. No
          other nexthop resolution process is performed, as the inter-AS link
          can be used for any Transport Class.</t>

          <t>If the inter-AS links should honor Transport Class, then the BN
          SHOULD follow procedures of an Ingress node described above, and
          perform nexthop resolution process. The interface routes SHOULD be
          installed in the Transport RIB belonging to the associated Transport
          Class.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Avoiding path-hiding through Route Reflectors<list>
          <t>When multiple BNs exist that advertise a RDn:PEn prefix to RRs,
          the RRs may hide all but one of the BNs, unless <xref
          target="RFC7911">ADDPATH</xref> is used for the Classful Transport
          family. This is similar to L3VPN option-B scenarios. Hence ADDPATH
          SHOULD be used for Classful Transport family, to avoid path-hiding
          through RRs.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Ingress node receiving service route with mapping community<list>
          <t>Service routes received with mapping community resolve using
          Transport RIBs determined by the resolution scheme. If the
          resolution process does not find an usable Classful Transport route
          or tunnel route in any of the Transport RIBs, the service route MUST
          be considered unusable for forwarding purpose.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Coordinating between domains using different community
      namespaces.<list>
          <t>Domains not agreeing on RT, RD, Mapping-community values because
          of independently administered community namespaces may deploy
          mechanisms to map and rewrite the Route-target values on domain
          boundaries, using per ASBR import policies. This is no different
          than any other BGP VPN family. Mechanisms employed in inter-AS VPN
          deployments may be used with the Classful Transport family also.</t>

          <t>The resolution schemes SHOULD allow association with multiple
          mapping communities. This helps with renumbering, network mergers,
          or transitions.</t>

          <t>Though RD can also be rewritten on domain boundaries, deploying
          unique RDs is strongly RECOMMENDED, because it helps in trouble
          shooting by uniquely identifying originator of a route, and avoids
          path-hiding.</t>

          <t>This document defines a new format of Route-Target
          extended-community to carry Transport Class, this avoids collision
          with regular Route Target namespace used by service routes.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="OAM considerations">
      <t>&lt;TBD&gt; BGP Clasful Transport will use a new [RFC 8029] OAM
      Target FEC Stack Subtype TBD. The FEC format will be similar to a VPN
      IPv4 prefix or VPN IPv6 prefix.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes following requests of IANA.</t>

      <section title="New BGP SAFI">
        <t>New BGP SAFI code for "Classful Transport". Value 76.</t>

        <t>This will be used to create new AFI,SAFI pairs for IPv4, IPv6
        Classful Transport families. viz:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>"Inet, Classful Transport". AFI/SAFI = "1/76" for carrying IPv4
            Classful Transport prefixes.</t>

            <t>"Inet6, Classful Transport". AFI/SAFI = "2/76" for carrying
            IPv6 Classful Transport prefixes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="New Format for BGP Extended Community">
        <t>Please assign a new Format (Type high = 0xa) of extended community
        <xref target="RFC4360">EXT-COMM</xref> called "Transport Class".</t>

        <t>It is a transitive extended community. This document uses this new
        Format with subtype 0x2 (route target) extended community.</t>

        <t>The Route Target thus formed is called "Transport Class" route
        target extended community.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Mechanisms described in this document carry Transport routes in a new
      BGP address family. That minimizes possibility of these routes leaking
      outside the expected domain or mixing with service routes.</t>

      <t>When redistributing between SAFI 4 and SAFI 76 Classful Transport
      routes, there is a possibility of SAFI 4 routes mixing with SAFI 1
      service routes. To avoid such scenarios, it is RECOMMENDED that
      implementations support keeping SAFI 4 routes in a separate transport
      RIB, distinct from service RIB that contain SAFI 1 service routes.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors thank Jeff Haas, John Scudder, Navaneetha Krishnan, Ravi
      M R, Chandrasekar Ramachandran, Shradha Hegde, Richard Roberts,
      Krzysztof Szarkowicz, John E Drake, Srihari Sangli, Vijay Kestur,
      Santosh Kolenchery for the valuable discussions.</t>

      <t>The decision to not reuse SAFI 128 and create a new address-family to
      carry these transport-routes was based on suggestion made by Richard
      Roberts and Krzysztof Szarkowicz.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8277"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4364"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4360"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4684"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7911"?>

      <reference anchor="SRTE"
                 target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-idr-segment-routing-te-policy-08">
        <front>
          <title>Advertising Segment Routing Policies in BGP</title>

          <author fullname="Previdi" initials="S" role="editor"
                  surname="Previdi"/>

          <date day="18" month="11" year="2019"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
